Register of the Alexandre Georgievich Tarsaidze papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- SUBJECT FILE, 1876-1977 (Boxes 11-30)
  - Russia
    - Nobility
      - Printed matter
        - Genealogies
          - Obolensky, Princes
            - Miscellany, 1905-1970 (Box-folder 25: 5)
            - Clippings, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 25: 6)
          - Sverbeev, Pleshko, N., Russkoe Istoriko-Rodoslovnoe Obshchestvo v Amerike, 1951 (Box-folder 25: 7)
          - Urussov, Princes, Pleshko, N., Russkoe Istoriko-Rodoslovnoe Obshchestvo v Amerike, 1955 (Box-folder 25: 8)
    - Ob"edinenie Russkikh IUristov b. Di Pi v Amerike, Vestnik, 1959 (Box-folder 25: 9)
    - Orthodox Church
      - General, Trifono-Pechengskii Monastery, miscellaneous material, undated (Box-folder 25: 10)
      - Clippings and tearsheets
        - Church in America (Box-folder 25: 11)
        - Church abroad [See also: SPEECHES AND WRITINGS], 1930s-1970 (Box-folder 25: 12)
    - Peter the Great, Emperor of Russia, miscellaneous material re Donizetti opera "Il borgomastro di Saardam,", 1973 (Box-folder 25: 13)
    - Pushkin, A., clippings, 1937-1975 (Box-folder 26: 1-2)
    - Revolution of 1905, clippings (Box-folder 26: 3)
    - Revolution of 1917
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1943-1969 (Box-folder 26: 4)
        - Mel'gunov, S., 1952-1957 (Box-folder 26: 5)
      - Memoirs, typescript
        - Anitchkoff, V., 1917-1922 (Box-folder 26: 6)
        - SHvetsov, D., undated (Box-folder 26: 7)
      - Printed matter, clippings and tearsheets
        - General (Box-folder 26: 8-10)
          Includes biographical material re Communists.
        - General (Box-folder 27: 1-6)
        - Gumberg, A., 1953 (Box-folder 28: 1)
        - Lenin, V., biographical material (Box-folder 28: 2-4)
        - Reilley, Sidney (Box-folder 28: 5)
        - Stalin, I. and Stalinists (Box-folder 28: 6)
        - "Zinov'ev letter,", 1966-1970 (Box-folder 28: 7)
    - Russian-American Information Bureau, letter of A. Tarsaidze, introducing organization, typescript, undated (Box-folder 28: 8)
    - Russo-Japanese War, clippings (Box-folder 28: 9-10)
    - Rossica, Society of Russian Philately Journal, 1955 (Box-folder 28: 11)
    - Siberia and the Far East, clippings (Box-folder 28: 12-13)
    - Solzhenitsyn, A., clippings [See also: SPEECHES AND WRITINGS and SUBJECT FILE/ World War I] (Box-folder 29: 1-5)
    - Stolypin, A., clippings (Box-folder 29: 6)
  - World War I
    - General
      - Association of Russian War Invalids of the First World War
        - Printed matter, Russkii Invalid, 1973 May (Box-folder 29: 7)
        - Miscellany, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 29: 8)
          Includes correspondence and legal papers.
      - Jagow, Gottlieb von (?), miscellaneous correspondence, typescript copies, 1914-1915 (Box-folder 29: 9)
      - Miasoedov, Col., clippings [See also: SPEECHES AND WRITINGS], 1965 (Box-folder 29: 10)
      - Navy
        - "Magdeburg Affair," including material re naval intelligence and codes
          - Clippings (Box-folder 29: 11)
          - Correspondence, 1959-1975 (Box-folder 29: 12)
        - Printed matter
          - General, Timirev, Rear-Adm. S., Baltiiskii Flot vo vremia voiny i revoliutsii, 1961 (Box-folder 29: 13)
          - Clippings (Box-folder 29: 14)
      - Ruzskii, Gen. V., clippings [See also: SPEECHES AND WRITINGS] (Box-folder 29: 15)
      - Sukhomlinov, Gen. V., clippings, tearsheets, photographic reproductions and other printed matter [See also: SPEECHES AND WRITINGS and SUBJECT FILE/Russia/Air Force/Navy], 1924-1966 (Box-folder 29: 16-18)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1943-1974 (Box-folder 29: 19)
      - Kerensky, A., 1944 (Box-folder 29: 20)
    - Printed matter
      - General
        - Andolenko, Gen., La Guerre 1914-1918 sur le front russe, 1965 (Box-folder 29: 21)
        - Budberg, Lieut.-Gen. Baron A., Vooruzhennyia sily Rossiiskoi Imperii v ispolnenii obshchesoiuznykh zadach i obiazanostei vo vremia voiny 1914-1917g., 1939 (Box-folder 29: 22)
        - Dartigues, L., La mission sanitaire chirurgicale française du Caucase 1er Juillet 1917-13 Juillet 1918, Paris, 1919 (Box-folder 30: 1)
        - Eristov, Prince A., "Velikii Kniaz' Sergei Mikhailovich," typescript excerpt, Russkii Invalid, 1939 (Box-folder 30: 2)
        - Headquarters of the Military Representative...of the Russian Army, Russia in the War, 1914-1918, 1919 (Box-folder 30: 3)
        - Konnaia gvardiia na voine, photograph album, 1914 (Box-folder 30: 4)
      - Clippings and tearsheets
        - General (Box-folder 30: 5-14)
        - German spies in Russia (Box-folder 30: 15)
          Includes A. Tarsaidze's letters to the editor.
      - Photographic reproductions (Box-folder 30: 16)
        Includes document changing name of St. Petersburg to Petrograd, 1914 August 18.
  - World War II, clippings (Box-folder 30: 17)
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1780s-1960 (Boxes 31-35)
  Printed matter, including prints, posters, chromolithographs, books, and albums of Caucasians in national dress; Georgian royalty, nobility, and national monuments; Russian tsars and emperors, Russian nobility, Russian Imperial Army and Navy; and miscellany related to St. Petersburg. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General, printed matter (Box 31)
    - Harper's Weekly, 1866
    - New York Times, Mid-Week Pictorial, 1919
  - Caucasus and Transcaucasus, tearsheets from album, prints, and posters, 1850s (Box 32)
    Caucasians in national dress and historical group scenes.
  - Georgia
    - Printed matter
      - "Genealogicheskaia tablitsa gruzinskago tsarskago doma s Bagrata III,", 1853
      - Berzhe, A. and Bakradze, D. eds., Zapiski obshchestva liubitelei kavkazskoi arkheologii, Tiflis, 175
    - Prints and posters
      - Gagarin, G., Chromolithographe Lemercier, chromolithographs of watercolor drawings of Georgian frescos in churches and palaces, 19th century
      - Portraits of Georgian royalty and nobility
        - Iraklii II, lithograph, undated
        - IUlon, Ioan and David, prints and copies of prints, undated
        - Gurieli, Princes, "Nekotorye iz deputatov Aziatskikh narodov...,", 1856
  - Russia
    - General (Box 33)
      - Novoe Vremia, photocopy, 1916 March
      - Tsars and Emperors of Russia, miscellaneous prints, undated
      - Miscellany, 1848-1969
        Includes posters, prints, drawings and programs.
    - Alexander II, Emperor of Russia. Printed matter
      - TSarstvovanie Imperatora Aleksandra II (v kartinakh), St. Petersburg, 1882
      - "Konchina Imperatora Aleksandra II," lithograph, 1881.
      - "Pamiatnyi list po sluchaiu iubileia...Aleksandra Nikolaevicha," St. Petersburg, 1880
    - Army, "Trubach. L. Gv. Kirasirskago... polka," color print, 1855
    - Navy
      - Sailor from ship Variag, fragment of poster, undated
      - Miscellany related to Russian-American naval relations, 1863
    - Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia
      - General
        - "Iz moego al'boma," personal family album of Empress Alexandra
        - Krasnyi Arkhiv, "Dnevnik Nikolaia Romanova," tearsheets, undated
      - Posters, Emperor Nicholas II and Russian Imperial Army
    - Nobility
      - "Carte des ordres de chevalerie de sa Majeste Czarine...,", 1780s
      - Spiski titulovannym rodam i litsam rossiiskoi imperi, Tipografiia pravitel'stvuiushchago senata, St. Petersburg, 1892
    - St. Petersburg (Box 34)
      - Maps, 1911, 1958
      - Printed matter
        - General, "Le palais imperial d'hiver,", 19th century
        - Dobuzhinskii, M., Peterburg v Dvatsat' pervom godu, 1923
  - Tarsaidze, A., scrapbooks of clippings
    - "Russian Naval Ball,", 1934 November
    - Social life, miscellany, 1935
    - Emperor Nicholas II - Last Monarch of Russia, announcements and reviews of film, 1956
    - Politics (especially Russophobia and misinterpretation of Russian history), clippings and letters to the editor, 1936-1956 (Box 35)
    - "Bal Blanc" and other social and charitable events, 1956-1960
- MAPS, 1648-1958 (Boxes 36-37)
  Maps of the South Pacific and the Russian Empire, including Georgia, arranged by subject.
  - General (Box 36)
    Rand McNally, "War-Planning Map of the World," undated; New Guinea and Papua, 1934; Oceania, 1840(?).
  - Russia
    - General, including Russian Empire, South Russia, Black Sea and Caucasus, Siberia and Maritime Provinces, 1648-1958
    - Georgia (Box 37)
      - Enlarged photographs of maps, 1905-1915
      - Tiflis, city plan, 19th century
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1880s-1960s (Photo file)
  404 prints, 51 postcards, 40 duplicates, 2 color transparencies, and 2 albums. Includes photographs of the Tarsaidze family; the Russian Imperial Army and Navy; World War I, the Revolution of 1917, and the Russian Civil War; Emperor Nicholas II, the Imperial family, and the Romanov family; and Georgia and the Transcaucasus. Arranged by subject.
  - 8 prints and 12 duplicates depicting A. Tarsaidze, 1905(?)-1920 (Envelope A)
  - 24 prints depicting the Tarsaidze and Eristavi families, 1900-1950s (Envelope B)
  - 5 prints depicting Russian Imperial Air Force, undated (Envelope C)
    Includes group photos of officers with Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia. Also includes portrait print of I. Sikorsky.
  - 29 prints depicting Russian Imperial Army, 1880s-1917 (Envelope D)
  - 39 prints depicting Russian Imperial Navy, 1865-1917 (Envelope mE)
  - 1 print depicting Lieut.-Gen. N. IUdenich with a group of Imperial Army officers, 1915 (Envelope F)
  - 33 prints depicting Russia in World War I, 1914-1917 (Envelope mG)
    Includes battle scenes, Red Cross work, street scenes, female soldiers of the Battalion of Death with their commander Maria Bochkareva, and portrait prints of soldiers, peasants, and nurses. Reproductions of Donald C. Thompson photographs.
  - 4 prints and 4 duplicates depicting the Russian Army of the Trans-Caucasus, 1914-1917(?) (Envelope H)
    Includes Dikaia Diviziia and the Emir of Bukhara.
  - 24 prints depicting street scenes in Petrograd during the Revolution of 1917 (Envelope mI)
    Includes A. Kerensky. Reproductions of Donald C. Thompson photographs, originally published in Blood Stained Russia, Leslie -Judge Co. Publishers, New York, 1918.
  - 33 prints depicting scenes of the Russian Civil War in the Caucasus, 1917-1918 (Envelope J)
  - 34 prints depicting Georgia, 1853-1922 (Envelope mK)
    Includes "Deputatsiia gruzinskago dvorianstva po povodu 100-letiia prisoedineniia Gruzii" and portrait prints of Prince G. Bagration, Prince I. Amilakhviri, and Prince Gurielli.
  - Photograph album of Georgia, 1900s (Album fL)
  - 2 prints depicting Karaims, 1913, 1916 (Envelope M)
    Includes the delegation to the celebration of the tricentenary of Romanov rule.
  - 19 prints and 7 duplicates related to G. Tarsaidze's book Katia: Wife Before God, 1880s-1950s (Envelope N)
    Includes portrait prints of Alexander II, Empress Maria, Ekaterina Dolgorukova, Ol'ga, Katia, and Georgii IUr'evskii.
  - 25 prints and 6 duplicates depicting the Imperial family, including scenes of military manoeuvres and ceremonies, 1910-1917 (Envelope O-P)
    Includes original prints by K. E. von Gan & Co., TSarskoe Selo.
  - 67 prints depicting Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1870s-1917 (Envelope Q-mR)
  - 9 prints and 1 duplicate depicting Alexandra, consort of Nicholas, Emperor of Russia, 1900s-1917 (Envelope S-mT)
  - 32 prints and 2 duplicates depicting Tsesarevich Aleksei Nikolaevich, 1908(?)-1917 (Envelope U-mV)
  - 32 prints and 1 duplicate depicting the Grand Duchesses Ol'ga, Tat'iana, Maria, and Anastasiia, 1905-1917(?) (Envelope W-mX)
    Includes scenes of their hospital work and a portrait print of Grand Duchess Tat'iana.
  - 30 prints depicting the Romanov family, 1880s-1960s (Envelope Y-Z)
  - 1 print depicting Grand Duke Mikhail Aleksandrovich and group of British noblemen, 1900s (Envelope mAA)
  - 1 print depicting Count V. Adlerberg, undated (Envelope BB)
  - 1 print depicting King Ferdinand I of Romania arriving in St. Petersburg, 1914 (Envelope mCC)
  - 1 print depicting Princess E. Obolenskaia in court dress, undated (Envelope DD)
  - 1 print depicting G. Rasputin in the company of society women, undated (Envelope mEE)
  - 1 print depicting Suliman Pasha Shapshal, Regent of Persia, 1907-1915 (Envelope FF)
  - 2 prints depicting P. Stolypin, 1911 (Envelope GG)
  - 1 print and 7 duplicates depicting ball in St. Petersburg, 1910(?) (Envelope HH)
  - 2 prints and 2 color transparencies of paintings by E. Vigee-Lebrun, one depicting Elizaveta Alekseevna, consort of Alexander I, Emperor of Russia, the other Princess Tatiana IUsupova, 1790s (Envelope mII)
  - 3 unidentified prints (Envelope JJ)
  - Photograph album of St. Petersburg, 1910s(?) (Album fKK)
  - 36 postcards of St. Petersburg and Leningrad, 1890s-1960s (Envelope LL)
  - 15 miscellaneous postcards (Envelope MM)
  - Print negatives (Envelope NN)
  - 35 mm. black and white negatives (Envelope OO)
- MOTION PICTURE FILM, 1944-1977 (Film shelf)
  Emperor Nicholas II, Last Czar of Russia and other films related to monarchy.
  - Coronation of Queen Elizabeth II, Castle Film Productions, 16 mm., sound, 1954 (Reel 1)
  - "News Parade of the Year" and "Old Time Movies," Castle Film Productions, 16 mm., sound, 1939 (Reel 2)
  - Memorial service (panikhida) for Russian Imperial Family at cathedral of Russian Church Abroad in New York, WCBS News, 16 mm., sound, 1968 (Reel 3)
  - Coronations of British monarchs up to George IV and coronation of Queen Elizabeth II, Pathegrams footage, 16 mm., silent and sound (Reel 4)
  - Russia in World War I, composite of still photographs in Tarsaidze collection, 16 mm., silent (Reel 5)
    Includes nursing activities of Grand Duchesses.
  - Emperor Nicholas II, Last Czar of Russia, sound (Reel 6)
    Also under title: Emperor Nicholas II - Last Monarch of Russia and Emperor Nicholas II. Includes incomplete duplicate, 2 copy negatives, 2 silent answer prints, and 1 incomplete lab test.
    Alternate Forms Available
    Videocassette (3/4" U-Matic)
  - Original footage of Emperor Nicholas II, Last Czar of Russia, Embassy Films, 16 mm., silent, 1956 (Reels 7-10)
    Access
    Use copy (DVD made from VHS copy) available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 78055_001_r2016.
    Videocassette (VHS)
    Includes Imperial family, miscellaneous footage.
  - Miscellaneous 35 mm. and 16 mm. fragments (Reel 11)
- SOUND RECORDINGS, 1955-1968, undated (Record cabinet)
  Includes Russian Imperial Cavalry march, memorial service for Imperial family, Soviet anthem, and recordings of interviews with A. Tarsaidze and others.
  - Sound recording of Anthems, Vol. I, Folkways Records, FP 88-1, 1955
    Use copy reference number: 78055_a_0006924
    These are chiefly instrumental performances of the national anthems.
  - Sound recording of "Cavalry March of Her Majesty's Regiment," 78 speed disc, undated
    Use copy reference number: 78055_a_0001774
    There are numerous scratches throughout this disc.
  - Sound recording of interview with A. Tarsaidze, I. Obolensky, and Adlerberg, 78 speed discs, undated
    Use copy reference number: 78055_a_0001775
    Describes the men's lives. In English.
  - Sound recording of "The Solemn Funeral Service for the Russian Imperial Family and all the Victims of Communist Terror," Brussels, 1968 July 17
    Use copy reference number: 78055_a_0006923
    The item title is culled from the heading of the back cover notes. In Russian.